《冰川时代2：融冰之灾》
我说, 这全球变暖真快热死我了!
Oh boy! This global warming is killing me.
这样太热，冰河世纪又太冷
This is too hot, the Ice Age was too cold.
怎样才能让你高兴啊!?
What would it take to make you happy?
这我喜欢
This I like.
哦! 你别想抓住我!
Oh, no, you won't catch me.
詹姆斯，不能跑，这是夏令营的规定
No running, James. Camp rules.
来抓我呀，树獭
Make me, sloth.
应该叫我先生! 待人尊重
Make me, sir. It's all about respect.
高台跳水
Water ball.
山米, 刚吃过饭不能剧烈运动!
Sammy, you just ate. Wait an hour.
海克托! 不! 不! 那不能尿尿!
Hector, no, no, no, you can't pee-pee there.
好吧，在那儿也行
OK, there is fine.
艾什莉，别抠鼻孔...
Ashley, stop picking your...
打糖果娃娃咯
Pińata!
等等 你们该先戴眼罩
Stop! You're supposed to wear blindfolds.
好啊
OK.
- 喂  该我打树獭了 - 该我
- Hey, it's my turn to hit the sloth. - Mine.
- 该我 - 该我
- Mine. - Mine.
你肚子里怎么没糖果？
Hey, you didn't have any candy in you.
- 那就埋了他! - 好!
- Let's bury him. - Yeah!
喂  孩子们怎么可以虐待树懒?
Hey, whoa. Who said you kids could torture the sloth?
曼尼，别扼杀了孩子们的创造力
Manny, don't squash their creativity.
曼尼! 迪亚戈! 我贴心贴背的好哥们
Hey, Manny, Diego, my bad mammals-jammals.
拉我一把吧
Wanna give a sloth a hand?
我的夏令营开张了 名字叫“希德领域”
Look, I opened my camp. "Campo del Sid".
意思是“希德的夏令营”
It means Camp of Sid.
恭喜，两种语言中，你都叫傻瓜
Congratulations. You're now an idiot in two languages.
别在这些小屁孩面前说
Not in front of the k-i-d-z.
小家伙们爱死我了 对吧，比利？
These little guys love me. Right, Billy?
别逼我吃了你
Don't make me eat you.
小子 所以说童言无忌嘛
They kid. That's why they're called kids.
我早说了, 希德, 要管一个营地你还不够格
I told you, Sid. You're not qualified to run a camp.
从几时起照看孩子也要看资格了?
What do qualifications have to do with childcare?
再说，这些孩子以我为榜样呢
Besides, these kids look up to me.
我是他们的榜样
I'm a role model to them.
看得出来
I can see that.
你们总觉得我是无能之辈, 可我也是这集体的一份子呀
You guys never think I can do anything, but I'm an equal member of this herd.
我建立了这集体,从现在起, 你们最好对我放尊重些
I made this herd, so you need to start treating me with some respect.
- 行了, 希德! - 希德, 我们说着玩的!
- Come on, Sid. - Sid, we were just kidding.
嘿! 我们来给毛象钉尾巴!
Hey, let's play pin-the-tail-on-the-mammoth.
- 好! - 希德
- Yeah! - Sid!
我有能耐我怕谁!
I can do stuff.
他们就是不把我放在眼里!
Won't give me their stupid respect.
等着瞧吧
I'll show 'em.
所以...最后... 小驴子终于找到妈妈了
And so, in the end, the little burro reached his mommy.
从此他们过着幸福快乐的日子
And they lived happily ever after.
- 好样的 - 我有问题
- Good job. - Question.
为什么小驴子要回家？ 怎么不和小兔子在一块儿？
Why does the burro go home? Why doesn't he stay with the rabbits?
因为...因为他想和家人在一块儿
Because... because he wanted to be with his family.
我认为他该去找驴小妹 多美丽的爱情故事呀
He should go with the girl burro. That's a better love story.
下次你讲小驴子的故事, 就让他谈情说爱
OK, well, when you tell your burro story, that's what he'll do.
小驴子难听死了, 严格说来应该叫他“野驴”
Burro is a demeaning name. Technically, it's called a wild ass.
好吧, 野驴小子回到了家, 找到了他的野驴老妈
Fine. The wild ass boy came home to his wild ass mother.
所以我才叫它小驴子
See, that's why I called it a burro.
小驴子应该很可怜，没得吃 这样才会感人
Could the burro have a grazing problem? Then he'd be more relatable.
- 无趣 - 没说服力
- Boring. - It's not believable.
- 大驴会吃小驴吗？ - 故事的结局不够完美
- Do burros eat their young? - It's not a good ending.
那样的话我都想吐了!
Sometimes I throw up.
他们从此幸福的生活在一起! 没有比这结局更让人满意的了
They lived happily ever after. You can't get more satisfying than that.
一个幸福的大家庭，本来就该这样
One big, happy family. That's the way it's supposed to be.
那你的“幸福的大家庭”在哪儿呢？
Where's your big, happy family?
然后, 饥饿的老虎, 吃了讨厌的小孩
Then the hungry tiger ate the pesky little kids.
- 你没事吧, 伙计? - 当然，怎会不好
- You OK, buddy? - Sure. Why not?
- 我以为... - 时间到了，故事结束
- I thought... - Story time's over. The end.
- 让路...别挡道 - 大家要去哪儿？
- Run for your lives! - Where's everybody going?
- 世界末日要来了 - 你说什么？
- The world's coming to an end. - What are you talking about?
去问东尼，世界要被洪水淹了
Fast Tony,he says the world's gonna flood.
各位! 我手上的装备威力无比
Folks, I hold in my hand a device so powerful,
它能把空气从天上抽下来!
it can actually pull air right out of the sky.
跟真的一样!
Yeah, right.
都过来! 都过来!
Gather round, gather round.
请教一下你有腮吗, 女士?
Pardon me, do you have gills, ma'am?
那你没法在水下呼吸!
So you can't breathe underwater?
我的这位助手将向你演示
My assistant here will demonstrate.
嘿! 有一股海洋的气息!
Hey, I can smell the ocean.
你在干嘛? 现在卖不出去了!
What are you doing? I can't sell that now.
应该插在嘴里, 白痴
You suck air through your mouth, you moron.
有了我伟大的发明，再按照我教的去做
Through its design and sturdy construction,
几兆年你也不会缺空气啦
you'll have plenty of air for eons to come.
当然啦, 效果因人而异
Of course, results may vary.
你干嘛要用世界末日来吓人？
Why are you scaring everybody with this doomsday stuff?
我是想混口饭吃啊，老兄
I'm trying to make a living here, pal.
这是我精准的气象预报
It's my weather forecast.
预计未来5天会有特大洪水
The five-day outlook calls for intense flooding
然后就是世界的末日!
followed by the end of the world.
本周后几天或许会有少许阳光
And a slight chance of patchy sunshine later in the week.
得了...别听他那一套
Come on, don't listen to him.
他为点蝇头小利连老妈都会卖
Fast Tony would sell his own mother for a grape.
你这算出价吗？
Are you making an offer?
别误会! 那种事我不干!
I mean, no, I would not.
你没听说，冰正在溶化吗？
Haven't you heard? The ice is melting.
你们瞧，这地整个被冰盖住
You see this ground, it's covered in ice.
一千年前它就被冰覆盖着
A thousand years ago, it was covered in ice.
一千年以后, 它还是会盖着冰
A thousand years from now, it will still be ice.
老兄，我不是怀疑你求生的本能...
Say, buddy, not to cast aspersions on your survival instincts or nothing,
但是猛犸象似乎快绝种了吧？
but haven't mammoths pretty much gone extinct?
- 你什么意思?？ - 我是说...“你”好像是最后一只猛犸象了
- What are you talking about? - About you being the last of your kind.
你满嘴臭蚂蚁味
Your breath smells like ants.
就算是吧，你最后见过另一只猛犸象是什么时候？
Be that as it may, when's the last time you saw another mammoth?
别听他胡说八道
Don't pay any attention to him.
猛犸象怎么会绝种! 它们是地球上最大的生物
Mammoths can't go extinct. They're the biggest things on Earth.
那恐龙呢？
What about the dinosaurs?
因为恐龙太狂妄，树敌太多
The dinosaurs got cocky and made enemies.
瞧! 有个傻瓜要跳悬崖自杀
Look. Some idiot's going down the Eviscerator.
最好不是我们的白痴朋友
Please tell me that's not our idiot.
好啦! 现在我数到三就要往下跳了!
OK, I'm gonna jump on the count of three.
1...
One...
2...
Two...
希德别乱动，我们上来救你
Sid, don't move a muscle. We're coming up.
跳! 跳! 跳!
Jump! Jump! Jump!
对不起
Sorry.
2 又千分之 3, 2 又千分之 4
Two and three one-thousandths, two and four one-thousandths...
希德! 你这是干嘛! 你快下来!
Sid, what are you doing? Get down from there.
决不，我要成为第一个跳悬崖的人
No. I'm gonna be the first to jump off the Eviscerator
以后你们就得尊敬我
and then you guys are gonna have to show me some respect.
如果你跳下去的话 只能得到我们对死人的尊敬
The only respect you'll get is respect for the dead.
算了吧，曼尼，他没傻到那份上!
Come on, Manny, he's not that stupid.
- 不过我也曾猜错 - 神兵天降...
- But I've been wrong before. - Geronimo!
小心
Hey, watch it.
我不能呼吸了 我的五脏六腑全走样了
I can't breathe. I think I just coughed up my spleen.
- 迪亚戈 把爪子收回去 - 对不起
- Diego, retract the claws, please. - Right. Sorry.
幸好我还了解你, 迪戈, 不然我会以为你怕水
If I didn't know you better, Diego, I'd think you were afraid of the water.
好吧, 好吧, 了解你是我的福气
OK, OK. Good thing I know you better.
大伙儿
Guys.
我想快脚东尼说对了
Fast Tony was right.
所有的东西都在溶化
Everything is melting.
要发洪水了 快 我们得去警告大家
It's all gonna flood. Come on, we gotta warn them.
或许可以把这里变成水上乐园
Maybe we can rapidly evolve into water creatures.
- 你真天才，希德 - 叫我“鱿鱼”吧
- That's genius, Sid. - Call me Squid.
这地方简直成垃圾堆了, 我竟然住在这儿
This whole thing's a piece ofjunk. I can't believe I live here.
怎么啦？
What?
不说芦苇啦, 我隆重推出革新小发明, 它名字叫...树皮
Forget reeds. I present you with this revolutionary gizmo we call bark.
- 轻凿一片, 漂浮水面 - 我来告诉你 什么可以浮吧
- It's so buoyant, it actually floats. - I'll show you something that floats.
好吧! 你们全死定了
All right, it's your funeral.
瞧瞧, 末日来临就是这景象!
See? This is exactly what I'm talking about.
猛犸象一般大的“绒”岩浆球从天而降
Giants balls of furry lava the size of mammoths raining from the sky.
你去用芦苇管吸空气吧
Go suck air through a reed.
各位，他说得对，洪水要来了
Listen to him. He's right about the flood.
我说得对？ 我是说...当然对啦
I am? I mean, yes, I am.
等等 你就是那个说不会有洪水的人
Wait. You said there wasn't going to be a flood.
我们为什么要相信你？
Why should we listen to you?
因为我们在上面亲眼所见 冰坝快破了
Because we saw what's up there. The dam's gonna break.
整个山谷会被水淹没
The entire valley's gonna flood.
真的会有洪水! 而且很快就会来
Flood's real, all right. And it's coming fast.
瞧瞧周围, 你们在盆地
Look around. You're in a bowl.
盆里的水就快满了，而且水也没出口
Bowl's gonna fill up. Ain't no way out.
那我们怎么办?
What are we gonna do?
除非你们能逃到山谷的尽头
Unless you make it to the end of the valley.
那儿有一条船, 它能救你们
There's a boat. It can save you.
- 我什么都看不见 - 不过
- I don't see anything. - But
要走趁早
y'all better hurry.
大地在融化, 冰墙在瓦解, 岩石在爆裂
Ground's melting, walls tumbling, rocks crumbling.
要想活命, 就得跟洪水赛跑
Survive that and you'll be racing the water,
三天之内，洪水就会来到这冰川之地
cos in three days' time, it's gonna hit the geyser fields.
轰隆!
Boom!
不过，有个好消息
There is some good news, though.
你们死得越多
The more of you die,
我就吃得越饱!
the better I eat.
我可没说，是你们的好消息
I didn't say it was good news for you.
让他来我课堂教书也不错！
He must have been a real pleasure to have in class.
什么鬼坝
Dam.
秃鹰说的都听到了吧，我们走
All right, you heard the scary vulture. Let's move out.
曼尼，你认为真的有船吗？
Manny, you really think there's a boat?
这我不敢说，可过不了几天这儿就成一片汪洋了
I don't know, but in a few days, this place is gonna be underwater.
那个方向，是我们唯一的活路
If there's any hope, it's that way.
曼尼，快走吧
Manny, let's go.
最右线车道被倒塌的冰崖所阻
Overturned glyptodont in the far right lane.
放眼望去都是受阻的交通
Traffic backed up as far as the eye can see.
哇，那里似乎有人死了
And it looks like there might be a fatality.
黑肉归我了!
I call the dark meat.
好啦! 大家快走吧! 来! 快快快! 进来!
Come on, everybody, let's go. Come on, come, come, come. Get in.
- 走吧! 爷爷! 快走吧!  - 我们得走啦!
- Come on, Grandpa, come on. - We have to go.
我就是不走! 我生在洞里, 也要死在洞里!
Well, I'm not leaving. I was born in this hole and I'll die in this hole.
干嘛非得带着这陀粪？
Do we have to bring this crap?
- 我们要去的地方也会有粪的啦 - 这可是我妈妈送我的礼物
- I'm sure there's crap where we're going. - This was a gift from my mother.
好啦, 都跟上! 都跟上!
OK, keep it moving, keep it moving.
曼尼! 我刚听说你要灭绝了
Manny, I just heard you're going extinct.
喂，你还没学会做人处世前 先学学说话婉转一点
Hey, if you ever master hygiene, try working on sensitivity.
- 我不会绝种 - 孩子们，瞧 最后一只猛犸象
- I'm not going extinct. - Kids, look. The last mammoth.
大概再也看不到另一只了
Well, you probably won't see another one of those again.
听到了吧
See?
我数数, 一, 二, 詹姆斯哪去了?
OK, one, two, three... Where is James?
斯图! 快点! 斯图!
Stu. Come on, Stu.
快点离开这大冰块!
Let's blow this ice-cube stand.
斯图
Stu.
大伙儿，我们是这山谷里 第一个有了自己的活动房屋的人
Folks, be the first in the valley to have your very own mobile home.
∮ 有一天当你想唱歌时 ∮
∮ Some day, when you're gonna sing ∮
∮ 或想要人们的注意时 ∮
∮ When you make us sing ∮
- 闭嘴，希德 - 好吧
- Shut up, Sid. - OK.
∮ 那是什么声音? 猛犸象全都入了土 ∮
∮ Stop, hey-hey...What's that sound..? All the mammoths are in the ground. ∮
别唱了，希德
Stop singing, Sid.
∮ 如果传宗接代你就拍拍手 ∮
∮ If you inherit the family, clap your hands
∮ 如果你的... ∮
∮ If you... ∮
希德，你得小心我再压你身上, 这次我压死你!
Sid, I'm going to fall on you again and this time I will kill you.
好吧, 有人不喜欢经典老歌
OK, someone doesn't like the classics.
万一你真说对了
What if you're right?
万一我真是最后一只猛犸象
What if I am the last mammoth?
曼尼，往好处想想，起码你还有我们
But Manny, look at the bright side, you have us.
这可不是什么好理由
Not your most persuasive argument, Sid.
- 猛犸象？ - 我就知道我绝不是最后一只
- Mammoths? - I knew I couldn't be the last one.
这我有直觉
I felt it in my gut.
绝种？ 少来！
Extinct? Come on.
曼尼全力冲刺 两人随行...
He's up by a couple of fifths, ahead by a tusk.
他就要战胜迪亚戈了!
And he's beating Diego as Diego's coming round the corner.
对不起 我的肚子在跟我捣蛋
Sorry. My stomach hates me.
真是空前绝后的臭!
Well, don't that put the "stink" in extinction?
真是恶心死了!
Nasty.
曼尼
Manny.
我想一个人静静
I need to be alone for a while.
你们先走吧 我随后就来
You go on ahead. I'll catch up.
“一”是世上最孤独的数字
One truly is the loneliest number.
这吹管真好用
These work great.
酷
Cool.
- 没抓到，没抓到  - 我来逮他们
- Missed me, now you gotta kiss me. - I'll get 'em.
- 他的哪一面在上？ - 我还以为那才是他的脸
- Which end is up? - I'd hide that face too.
- 嗨, 丑八怪! - 噢! 屁股是用来坐的
- Hey, ugly. - I gotta sit on that.
嗨!
Gotcha.
好了, 我要进去了!
OK, I'm going in.
- 希德 - 怎么啦？
- Sid. - What?
- 射得好 - 注意背后!
- Nice miss. - Cover your side.
- 我感觉有风 - 笑一个
- I felt some breeze in that one. - Smile.
- 来抓我呀 - 喂
- Out of my way. - Hello.
希德
Sid
在这儿
Over here.
- 投降吗？ - 决不
- Surrender? - Never.
酷
Cool.
往下射
Smoke them.
有谁问起, 就说他们有 50个, 而且他妈是响尾蛇
If anyone asks, there were 50 of 'em and they were rattlesnakes.
- 来呀, 小猫咪 - 别搞错了, 两个小无赖!
- Here, kitty, kitty. - Big mistake, you miscreants.
小无赖?
Miscreants?
迪亚戈，他们是负鼠
Diego, they're possums.
撤退
Retreat.
我想就剩你和我了
I guess it's just you and me now.
我就知道，不可能只有我
I knew it. I knew I wasn't the only one.
对呀，每个人都会从树上摔下来 只是他们不肯承认罢了
Everyone falls out of the tree now and then. They just don't admit it.
等等，你说什么？
Wait. What?
要我们抓着那些树枝谈何容易
Some of us have a tough time holding on to branches.
我们又不是蝙蝠什么的, 我们没有翅膀来保持平衡
It's not like we're bats or something. We don't have wings to keep us up.
你在...树上...因为...？
And you were in the tree because...?
我在找我兄弟，他们老是惹麻烦
I was looking for my brothers. They are always in trouble.
兄弟？ 你是说...还有更多？
Brothers? You mean there's more?
当然
Sure.
- 我们一大堆哦 - 哪里？
- There's lots of us. - Where?
到处都是 石头地下，地洞里面
Everywhere. Under rocks. In holes in the ground.
我们通常在夜里出来, 免得被鸟抓着
Usually we come out at night so birds don't carry us off.
救命啊!
Help! Help!
Help!
哇！我得改姓了 你居然又找到一只猛犸象
Well, shave me down and call me a mole rat. You found another mammoth.
哪里？ 等等，我还以为猛犸象绝种了
Where? Wait a minute. I thought mammoths were extinct.
- 你们看着我干嘛？ - 不知道...或许因为你是猛犸象吧
- What are you looking at me for? - I don't know. Because you're a mammoth.
我？别扯啦，我才不是猛犸象，我是负鼠
Me? Don't be ridiculous. I'm not a mammoth. I'm a possum.
对呀，说得好 我是大角羚羊，他是我朋友獾
Right. Good one. I'm a newt. This is my friend, the badger.
他是我另一位朋友鸭嘴兽
And my other friend, the platypus.
我才不要做鸭嘴兽，让他做吧
Why do I gotta be the platypus? Make him the platypus.
- 这些人找你麻烦吗，姐姐？- 姐姐？
- This guy giving you trouble, sis? - Sis?
对呀，他们是我弟弟 负鼠 负鼠 负鼠
That's right. These are my brothers. Possum, possum, possum.
她脑子里八成是哪根筋搭错了
I don't think her tree goes all the way to the top branch.
曼尼, 都快灭绝了, 就别挑三拣四了
Manny, brink of extinction's a bad time to be picky.
有了，邀她与我们同行吧
Hey, she should come with us.
你疯啦，不行
Are you insane? No way.
好吧
OK.
曼尼请你们跟我们一起躲避洪水
Manny wants me to ask you if you'd like to escape the flood with us.
- 我宁愿暴死街头 - 这好办
- I'd rather be road kill. - That can be arranged.
真逗! 我来和我弟弟谈谈
Funny. Let me have a little word with my brothers.
艾丽你疯啦，我们才不要跟他们走
Ellie, are you crazy? We're not going with them.
听着，我们如果只能晚上走，一定赶不及
Look, we'll never make it in time if we only travel at night.
这些家伙能在路上保护我们, 怎么样?
These guys can protect us out in the open. What do you say?
你干吗邀请他们?
Why did you invite them?
因为你们可能是世上剩的最后两只猛犸象
Cos you might be the only two mammoths left on Earth.
他说得对
He has a point.
对不起, 我几时参加两情一线牵了?
Sorry, when did I join this dating service?
我和弟弟们很高兴和你们一起走
My brothers and I would be delighted to come with you.
只要你们对我们客气点
If you treat us nicely.
看到了吧，这就是很不友善
See that? That's the total opposite of nice.
上路前能吃点心也不错
Maybe we'll have a snack before we hit the road.
你想吃了我们？ 放马过来吧
You want a piece of us? Let's go.
炸弹开花！
Banzai!
- 我来逮他...噢 - 退后！退后！
- I got 'em. - Back! Back!
我们的绝招是...身上有病菌
You know the best part? We're carrying diseases.
好啦，由于希德的促成，我们才能同行
OK, thanks to Sid, we're now travelling together.
不管你高兴与否，我们都得像个大家庭
And like it or not, we're going to be one big, happy family.
我是爸爸，艾丽是妈妈
I'll be the daddy, Ellie will be the mommy.
迪亚戈是叔叔，专门负责吃掉惹毛我的小孩
And Diego will be the uncle who eats the kids who get on my nerves.
趁脚下的地还没垮之前，快走吧
Now, let's move it before the ground falls out from under our feet.
我还以为肥仔都很和气
I thought fat guys were supposed to be jolly.
我才不肥！是毛让我看起来很巨大
I'm not fat. It's this fur, it makes me look big.
- 毛太松散了 - 哦
- It's poofy. - OK.
就是肥嘛
He's fat.
各位，为了逃洪灾 现在正是减肥的好时机
Escaping the flood is the perfect time to shed those unsightly pounds
快来买快脚东尼的“逃难减肥餐”
with Fast Tony's Disaster Diet.
夫人，你看起来像毛茸茸的大怪兽
You, ma'am, you look like a big, fat, hairy beast.
减个一、两吨的肥肉如何？
How would you like to lose a ton or two?
正合我意
Would I ever.
薇拉，别听他的 你已经苗条的像根竹竿
Don't listen to him, Vera. You're already thin as a twig.
朋友，我正好也有秘方 专治你你快瞎的眼睛
I also have the perfect cure for your eyesight, my blind friend.
照这种速度，永远也到不了
We'll never make it at this pace.
艾丽，现在很安全，你可以卸下伪装了
Ellie, it's OK, you can lose the camouflage. You're safe.
好 安全？ 少来！
OK. Safe? Please.
你俩儿去探个路
Crash, Eddie, you two go scope it out.
- 你看到什么？ - 队长，前方看似安全
- What you got? - Perimeter all clear.
- 知道了，完毕 - 嗯...完毕...噢！
- Roger that. One-niner, over. - Roger, over, victor...
- 喂？ - 安全
- Guys. - All clear.
老鹰！
Hawk!
- 你们在干嘛？ - 装死呀
- What are you doing? - Playing dead.
- 曼尼，你为什么不装死？ - 因为...我是猛犸象
- Manny, why don't you do that? - Because I'm a mammoth.
但你会装着玩，对吧？
But you'd do it for treats, right?
它走了吗？
Is he gone?
你安全了，起来吧
You're safe. Get up.
哎哟
Man.
还好有你在，不然那老鹰 一定会冲下来把我抓去当晚餐
If you weren't here, that hawk would have swooped down and snatched me for dinner.
我的表弟维尔敦就这下场
That's how cousin Wilton went.
哎哟, 我可真同情你, 真的
Boy, I really feel for you. I do.
你们这物种就剩你一头了, 这种滋味我真是没法想象!
I can't even imagine what it'd be like to be the last one of your species.
- 我不是最后一只 - 你真有颗伟大勇敢的心
- I'm not the last one. - You brave, brave soul.
没错，决不放弃希望
That's right. Don't give up hope.
艾丽
Ellie.
看看我们的脚印
Look at our footprints.
一样的形状
They're the same shape.
我怎知那些不都是你的？
Well, how do I know those aren't your footprints?
呃  那么
Well, then,
看看我们的影子
look at our shadows.
很吻合
We match.
你对啦，果然一样
You're right. They're the same.
那你一定也是负鼠
You must be part possum.
你想得美!
You wish.
迪亚戈，连地都走得比你快 快吧
Diego, there are whole continents moving faster than you.
我们得赶上前面的大队
We gotta catch up with the others.
喂  别闹了
Hey. Knock it off.
别唧唧哇哇的, 就像大老虎, 找点乐子吧!
Cry me a river, blubber-tooth tiger. Have some fun.
这冰已经够薄了, 经不住你们这么闹腾
The ice is thin enough without you two wearing it down.
得了 迪亚戈 冰虽然薄
Diego, come on. The ice may be thin
还能承受 十吨重的猛犸象和九吨重的“负鼠”
but it's strong enough to hold a ten-ton mammoth and a nine-ton possum.
有人落水啦！
Mammal overboard!
艾丽, 快起来! 你再装死, 就死定了
Ellie, get up. If you play dead, you'll be dead.
看着我!
Look at me.
迪亚戈
Diego.
快！ 迪亚戈
Come on, Diego. Come on.
可能会有点儿痛
This may sting a little.
- 那是哪一种生物？- 不知道
- What in the animal kingdom was that? - I don't know.
现在起，陆上安全，水里不安全
From now on, land-safe, water-not safe.
你是我见过最勇敢的
That was the bravest thing I've ever seen.
- 其实没什么啦...我... - 我可不是称赞你
- It was nothing. I... - It's not a compliment.
对负鼠来说, 勇敢就是笨
To a possum, bravery is just dumb.
- 对呀，我们没骨气 - 蔫了吧叽的
- Yeah, we're spineless. - Lily-livered.
或许就是因为猛犸象爱逞能 才会弄得快要绝种了
Maybe mammoths are going extinct because they get in danger.
以后该学会逃命
Maybe you should run away more.
精辟呀! 谢谢你的忠告
Good point. Thanks for the advice.
助人为乐嘛!
Happy to help.
她居然说这话? “勇敢就是笨, 以后该学会逃命”
Do you believe her? "Bravery is dumb. Maybe you should run away more".
她真让人生气，又固执，又没见识
She's infuriating and stubborn and narrow-minded.
你喜欢她
You like her.
- 才没 - 别担心，我会替你保密
- I do not. - Don't worry. Your secret's safe with me.
- 还有你的秘密 - 什么秘密？
- And so is yours. - What secret?
你知道的呀，就是你不会游泳
You know, the one where you can't swim.
荒谬
That's ridiculous.
随你啦，但我们的世界快溶化了
Fine. But we're living in a melting world.
你的那些恐惧也迟早要面对
You're going to have to face your fear sooner or later.
到啦
Almost there.
- 准备好了吗，艾迪？ - 好了
- OK. Ready, Eddie? - Set.
滚起来!
Let's roll.
等等我!
Wait for me.
别停啊 我先走一步 我在终点等你们吧
No brakes. Gotta roll. Meet you at the other end.
那么, 你真觉得她配我正合适?
So you think she's the girl for me?
对呀，她很有趣，你很无趣
Yeah. She's tons of fun and you're no fun at all.
她能补你的短
She completes you.
是
Yeah.
喂  曼尼 你可以用树枝把我射到那边的池塘吗？
Hey, Manny. Can you pull back the tree and shoot me into the pond?
- 不行 - 拜托啦
- No. - Come on.
你这样的态度怎能吸引艾丽呢？
You expect to impress with that attitude?
我不想讨她欢心!
I don't want to impress.
那你干嘛要费尽唇舌 让她相信自己是猛犸象？
Why are you trying to convince her she's a mammoth?
因为她就是！ 管她是否自认是负鼠
Because that's what she is. I don't care if she thinks she's a possum.
- 总之不能同时是两种生物 - 正好相反，曼尼先生
- You can't be two things. - Au contraire, Man-fered.
例子有 牛蛙、龙鸟、还有熊猫
Tell that to the bullfrog, chicken hawk or turtledove.
你再啰唆，有得你瞧的
He's never gonna let up on you.
如果你乖点儿，对大伙儿都有好处
It'll be easier on all of us if you just go with it.
你要我干嘛？
So what do you want me to do?
扳回树枝，把我射到那边的池塘
Pull the tree and shoot me into the pond.
能这样吗？
I don't know.
呃...如果你没胆，我们可以去找艾丽
If you're too lame to do it, we can get Ellie.
别 别，我行 我行
No, no, no. No, I can do it. I can do it.
好耶，好耶 快，快
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Come on, come on.
- 你以前干过吗？- 才一百万次而已
- Have you done this before? - Only a million times.
远点儿, 远点儿
Farther, farther, farther.
好 发射
Perfect. Fire!
我会飞啦
Yeah! I can fly!
我相信我会飞
I believe I can fly..
克来什？
Crash!
克来什！克来什！
Crash! Crash!
- 克来什，你没事吧？ - 怎么啦？
- Crash, are you OK? - What happened?
- 曼尼把他往树上射 - 你是怎么回事啊？
- Manny shot him out of a tree. - What's wrong with you?
- 他说没问题的呀！- 你还真相信他？
- He said he could do it. - And you listened to him?
克来什！去哪儿都行，可别去天国呀
Crash, whatever you do, don't go into the light.
我能帮上什么忙吗？
Can I help in any way here?
你帮得够了
You've done enough.
- 这下你高兴了吧 - 克来什！克来什！别离我而去
- Are you happy now? - Crash, Crash, don't leave me.
谁能掩护我？
Who's gonna watch my back?
谁是我一起去捣蛋？
Who's gonna be my wingman of mayhem?
谁能和我一起滚树干？
Who's gonna roll in that dung patch with me?
滚树干？
Dung patch?
- 等等 我的腿 我能站啦 - 他能站
- Wait. My legs. I can stand. - He can stand.
- 我能跑啦 - 他能跑...真是奇迹啊
- I can run. - He can run. It's a miracle.
感谢上苍
Hallelujah!
我还能说什么？ 他们是男孩儿 他们使我的生命更刺激
What can I say? They're boys. They make my life a little adventure.
你们俩死定了!
You guys are so dead. Thanks for embarrassing me.
别打脸!
Not the face.
艾丽 艾丽 我也要
Ellie, Ellie, me too.
她其实还不错
She's not half bad.
有点儿疯狂，让人迷惑，但很甜美
Crazy and confused, but sweet.
又如何？
So?
那你还犹豫什么？
So what's holding you back?
我的家人
My family.
你可以重组一个家庭呀
You can have that again, you know.
不，希德，我不行
No, Sid, I can't.
好啦，好啦，但是，但是，你想想...
OK, OK, but think about it. I mean, if you let this chance go,
如果错过这次机会，你的物种就会灭绝...太自私了吧
you're letting your whole species go and that's just... that's just selfish.
我想我大概还活着
I think I'm starting to get through to him.
- 哈哈...等等...逮到你啦 - 你太慢啦
- Wait, wait. I got you. - Slowpoke.
- 要帮忙吗？ - 不，不用，只是喘口气
- Need help? - No, no. Just catching my breath.
- 你卡住了 - 我没有
- You're stuck. - I am not.
那好，我们走吧
All right, then, let's go.
我不能
I can't.
我是卡住了
I'm stuck.
用牙去抬树干，不是比较简单吗？
Don't you think that picking them up like this would be easier?
艾丽
Ellie?
我知道这地方
I know this place.
其实...我能感觉...我和他们不一样
You know, deep down, I knew I was different.
我比其他小负鼠们都大一点
I was a little bigger than the other possum kids.
好啦...大很多
OK, a lot bigger.
哦...我终于明白为何 没有负鼠男孩喜欢我
Now I understand why the possum boys didn't find me appealing.
真可惜，不过对猛犸象来说，你...
That's too bad, because as far as mammoths go, you're...
- 你知道的... - 知道什么？
- you know. - What?
很有魅力
Attractive.
- 真的？ - 当然
- Really? - Sure.
我的哪里有魅力？
What about me is attractive?
我也不知道
I don't know.
呃，你的...
Well, there's your
臀部
butt.
我臀部怎样？
What about it?
很...
It's
丰满
big.
你只是随便说说罢了
You're just saying that.
不...不是...我说真的
No, no, no, I mean it.
很丰满 我见过最丰满的臀部
It's huge. Biggest darn butt I've ever seen.
你真好
That is really sweet.
今天真是疯狂...
What a crazy day.
我早上起来还是负鼠 现在却成了猛犸象
This morning I woke up a possum and now I'm a mammoth.
哇塞，曼尼和艾丽今天进展神速
Boy, Manny sure took a big leap with Ellie today.
对呀
Sure did.
虽然情势不明 但是曼尼终究还是奋勇向前
He stood on the shore of uncertainty and dove right in. Splash.
他克服恐惧的方法很勇敢，对吧？
Kind of brave, huh? The way he faced his fear.
我又不恐惧，怎么会知道？
I wouldn't know. Sabres don't feel fear.
少来啦，所有的动物都会恐惧 这就是动物和石头的分别
Come on, all animals feel fear. It's what separates us from, say, rocks.
石头是没有恐惧的
Rocks have no fear.
- 而且石头会沉 - 你倒底想说什么？
- And they sink. - What are you getting at, Sid?
或许你会惊讶，我也曾有恐惧的经验
It may surprise you to know that I, too, have experienced fear.
你？不会吧？
No. You?
哦，当然  虽然似乎不可能...
Yeah. Yes, as impossible as it seems,
但是树獭有天敌 他们会伤害、甚至“吃掉”我们
the sloth has natural enemies that would like to harm or otherwise "kill" us.
- 总有原因吧？ - 因为我们很美味
- I wonder why? - Jealousy, mostly.
但我要说的是...恐惧是天性
But the point is that fear is natural.
恐惧是属于猎物的
Fear is for prey.
那么...你就是水的猎物咯
Well, then, you're letting the water make you its prey.
就这么跳下去，然后相信你的本能
Justjump in and trust your instincts.
很多动物从小就会游泳
You know, most animals can swim as babies.
对老虎来说，就像狩猎时 朝你可怜的猎物匍伏向前
And for a tiger, it's like crawling on your belly to stalk helpless prey.
不过要快点儿，懂吧？ 扒，踢，扒，踢
But faster, OK? Now, claw, kick, claw, kick.
我在潜近猎物 扒，踢
I'm stalking the prey. Claw, kick.
现在回头看，假装被跟踪
I look back over my shoulder to see if I'm being followed.
然后吸口气...
And I'm breathing.
我在潜近...我在潜近...然后...啊
And I'm stalking and I'm stalking and I'm...
- 我就摔下来了 - 纠正一下, 你沉下去了
- I'm falling. - Correction. You're sinking.
好像石头一样
Kind of like a rock.
呼嘿，猛犸象有特殊技能吗，比方翻滚？
Hey, do we do any special tricks like roll over?
还是会用我们的身体左右摇晃？
Or do we just throw our weight around?
对不起
Whoops. Sorry.
我不知道自己的特长是什么？
I don't know my own strength yet.
艾丽，你知道我们现在有机会 来拯救我们的物种吗？
Ellie, do you realise that now we have a chance to save our species?
- 真的？ 怎么做？ - 呃...你知道的呀
- Really? How are we gonna do that? - Well, you know...
你刚才是...？
Did you just...?
我才成为猛犸象五分钟 你就想勾引我！
I'm not a mammoth for five minutes and you're hitting on me?
我不是说...现在，是过一阵子啦
I wasn't saying... Not right now. In time.
我只是说...那是我们的责任
I was just saying that it's our responsibility.
什么!?
What?
我...说错了...我...
All right, that came out wrong. I...
你很漂亮，不过我们才刚认识
You're very pretty, but we just met...
责任？ 只是做你该做的，是吗？
Responsibility? Just doing your duty? Is that it?
准备好要做最大的牺牲，来拯救你的物种
Ready to make the ultimate sacrifice to save your species.
我跟你说白了吧，你今晚不能拯救 哪一个晚上都不行
I got some news for you. You're not saving the species tonight or any other night.
- 呃...进展如何？ - 还不错
- So, how did it go? - Not bad.
好啦，我们走吧 白天我们跟你走
OK, let's go. We travelled with you all day,
晚上你们跟我走
now you're coming with us at night.
但我们晚上看不见
But we can't see at night.
那就好好享用洪水吧
Then enjoy the flood.
我连看都不想看他
I can't even look at him.
变态！
Pervert.
交朋友, 你走到哪儿都是这么交朋友的?
Making friends everywhere you go. Just making friends.
- 小心! 有树桩 - 这会儿没了
- Watch out, there's a stump. - Not anymore.
我...以为大家可以走近点儿？
I thought we could walk together.
克来什，去问他为什么会这么认为？
Crash, ask the mammoth why he thinks that.
她说，她认为你是个痞子，要你走开
She said she thinks you're ajerk and to go away.
她没说...噢！
She didn't say...
我说...如果我们能多相处...噢！
Look, maybe if we spend more time...
告诉他，我需要多一点儿私人空间
Tell him that I need a little personal space right now.
- 她说你去跳湖 - 负鼠万岁
- She said go jump in a lake. - And possums rule.
- 我听不见她说什么 - 你想要什么...奖章？
- I can hear her, you know. - What do you want? A medal?
移一下位置
Stop moving.
谢谢，呼
Thank you.
曼尼，艾丽，牵鼻子
Manny, Ellie. Lock trunks.
快！
Now!
克来什，艾迪，抓住那边的危崖
Crash, Eddie. Grab on to that ledge.
- 现在该怎么办？- 快...去做
- Funny. Now what's your real plan? - Just do it.
- 再见，艾迪 - 再见，克来什
- Bye, Eddie. - Bye, Crash.
- 再见，艾丽 - 快去
- Bye, Ellie. - Go now.
对不起 如果我刚才说的冒犯了你
I'm sorry if what I said before offended you.
“如果”是什么意思？
What do you mean "if" it offended me?
你“当然”冒犯了她
That it offended her!
我只是说“如果”会冒犯了你
I mean that, that it offended you.
- 你只不过是反应过度 - 什么?
- You just overreacted, that's all. - What?
- 收回你刚说的 - 你什么狗屁“反应过度”
- Take it back. - There are other lives at stake here.
- 他说的有道理 - 毫无道理!
- He's got a point. - He's got nothing.
- 只是误会 - 说话不知检点
- It was a misunderstanding. - It was insensitive.
- 道歉 - 为何要我道歉？是她反应过度
- Apologise. - Why me? She overreacted.
- 快道歉 - 不
- Just apologise. - No.
- 快 - 好吧，对不起
- Do it. - OK, I'm sorry.
什么？
What?
- 他说得对，是我反应过度 -  你是说...
- He's right. I overreacted. - You mean...
别说了，不然我过去给你一爪
Not another word or I'll come down there and push you over myself.
没问题
I got it. I got it.
我没问题
I got it.
曼尼，艾丽，快跑
Manny, Ellie, run! Run!
我想我们终于一起做对了一件事
I guess we finally did something right together.
呵  别管我，我只不过是挂在悬崖罢了
Hey, don't mind me. Just hanging off the edge of a cliff here.
- 还记得以前的好日子吗？ - 什么好日子？
- Remember the good old days? - Which good old days?
你知道的啦...昨天、上星期
You know. Yesterday, last week.
那些孩子们在我们脚边嘻笑打闹的日子
Back when the trees went up and down and the ground stayed under our feet.
没错，那些的确是好日子
Yep. Those were the good days.
那时候负鼠就是负鼠，猛犸象就是猛犸象
Possums were possums and mammoths were mammoths.
- 该睡了 - 是
- We should get some sleep. - Yeah.
秃鹰说明天就是世界末日
Tomorrow's the day the vulture said we're all going to die.
等等
Wait a minute.
你们需要帮忙吗？
Can I help you?
嗯...这才叫“尊敬”
Now, that's what I call respect.
好极了
Nice.
这里一定有人喜欢希德
Somebody here likes Sid.
谁是设计师？ 简直太棒了
Who is your decorator? I mean, this is fabulous.
火王
Fire King.
火王？ 嗯 也该是有人注意到我潜能的时候了
Fire King? Well, you know, it's about time someone recognised my true potential.
火来吧
Let there be fire.
好烫，好烫
Hot, Hot
要是大伙儿能看到我这么风光就好啦
If only the guys could see me now.
这不是极好就是极坏
This is either really good or really bad.
别别别
No, no, no.
我是火王 为什么要杀火王
Me Fire King. Why kill Fire King?
杀了千年火王对你们有什么好处？
A thousand years' bad juju for killing Fire King.
极热的岩石从地心升起
Super-heated rock from Earth's core is surging to the crust,
溶化了千年的冰山
melting ice built up over thousands of years.
你们有很高的文明 我们定能一起想出解决的好办法
You're a very advanced race. Together, we can look for a solution.
我们已经有办法了 牺牲火王
We have one, sacrifice the Fire King.
- 这不太文明吧 - 值得一试
- Well, that's not very advanced. - Worth a shot.
不 不
No! No!
他是恶咒!
Bad juju!
水! 水!
Water? Water!
告诉过你，睡前别喝水
Crash, I told you not to drink before bed.
不是我弄的啦 起码不全是我
I didn't do this. At least, not all of it.
- 怎么回事？ - 我们睡过头了，得快走
- What's happening? - We overslept. We need to move.
万一我们是物种的最后两个
What if we're the last creatures left alive?
我们得在地球上繁衍生命!
We'll have to repopulate the Earth.
怎么做？ 这里不是公的，就是我们的姊妹
How? Everyone's either a dude or our sister.
噢  嗨  曼尼
Hi. Hey, Manny.
哇，昨晚真神奇 你们一定猜不出来发生了何事
Wow. What a night. You'll never guess what happened.
我敢打赌说你一定是梦游了
You were sleepwalking.
不不，我被迷你树獭族绑架了
No, no, no. I was kidnapped by a tribe of mini sloths.
- 那是我第二个猜测 - 他们崇拜我
- That was gonna be my second guess. - And they worshiped me.
虽然他们把我扔进融岩火坑 但是他们还是崇拜我的
I mean, sure, they tossed me into a flaming tar pit, but they worshiped me.
希德，你在作梦 快走吧，水升得比我们走得还快
You were dreaming. Come on, the water's rising faster than we're moving.
我刚说啦，我被绑架，被崇拜 我...我...大伙儿...
I'm telling you, I was kidnapped. I was worshiped. Guys.
呃...算了
Fine.
能慢点儿吗？ 我快死了
Can we slow down a little? I'm dying here.
我只是打个比方
It was just a figure of speech.
他们一动也不动  看着我们
They just sit there, watching us.
真希望能知道他们在想什么？
I wish I knew what they were thinking.
食物，神圣的食物
Food, glorious food...
叫人垂涎三尺
we're anxious to try it...
一日三回盛宴
Three banquets a day...
我们钟爱的食物
our favorite diet!
想像一块长毛象肉排
Just picture a mammoth steak...
不论炸、烤或清炖
fried, roasted....or stewed...
噢，美味令人赞叹的食物
food, wonderful food...
神圣的食物
marvelous food...
食物，神圣的食物
Food, glorious food...
神圣的食物
glorious fooood!
麻油负鼠酒冒着火舌
poached possums or flamb?
鲜煮树懒汤
Broth made from a sloth...
烤奶油剑齿虎酥
or savored to souffl?
整天冥想怎会有如此命运
Why should we debate it? True you've nothing, but food!
噢，食物，神奇的食物
Oh...foood, magical food
奇妙令人赞叹的食物
wonderful food, marvelous foood!
食物，神圣的食物
Food, glorious food...
从死尸剥下的肉
Flesh, picked off the dead ones!
不管发臭、腐烂还是被咬过
We're famished for food...
很快进了我们五脏庙
soon, we'll be the fed ones!
只要想到腐败的臭肉
Just thinking of putrid meat...
心情不禁飞扬起来
puts us in the mood!
因为食物，神圣的食物
Oh, food, glorious food...
神奇的食物，美妙的食物
marvelous food, wonderful food...
美丽的食物
beautiful food...
神奇的食物
magical food...
神圣的...
glorious...
食物!
Foood!
现在知道他们在想什么了吧
There. Now you know what they were thinking.
食物，神圣的食物
Food, glorious food
- 希德 - 干嘛? 很容易朗朗上口
- Sid! - What? It's catchy.
- 成功了! - 总算没有让秃鹰看扁
- We made it. - Yeah, we showed those scary vultures.
一点热水和蒸汽，算什么?
It's just a little hot water and steam. How bad could it be?
我刚刚有点失禁，拉了一屁股
I just did something involuntary and messy.
好啦，走吧
OK, come on.
曼尼，回来!简直是地雷区
Manny. Get back. It's a minefield out there.
唯一的办法是笔直通过
There's only one way to go. Straight through.
我不想死前被烫熟拔毛，谢谢
Straight through? We'd like to keep the fur on our bodies, thank you.
- 我们回头，绕过去 - 不!没时间了
- We'll head back and go around. - There's no time.
水坝会溃堤淹死我们
The dam will burst before we make it. We'll drown.
走过这里会被射成蜂窝
If we go through this, we get blown to bits.
- 前进! - 回头!
- We go forward. - We go back.
- Forward. - Back.
- 我可以发言吗? - 不行!
- Can I say something? - No.
- 你很固执，刚愎自用 - 大概这就证据确凿
- You are so stubborn and hard-headed. - Well, I guess that proves it.
证明我是真的长毛象
I am a mammoth.
- 我们走 - 请便
- Come on. - Fine.
淹死算是温和的死法
I don't know. Drowning sounds like a much gentler way to go.
射成蜂窝听起来...比较干脆
Blown to bits sounds so sudden.
他会害死自己 曼尼!等等!
He's going to get himself killed. Manny, wait.
曼尼
Manny.
孩子们看!最后一头长毛象!
Kids, look, the last mammoth.
听说你们快绝种了
I just heard you're going extinct.
- 叫负鼠长毛象不伦不类 - 她觉得你很没品
- You can't be two things. - She thinks you're ajerk.
你幸福的大家庭呢?
Where's your big, happy family?
你有什么毛病?
What's wrong with you?
曼尼!起来!要走了!
Manny, come on. We gotta go. Now!
那边!
That way.
千万不要单独留下小孩 没人看顾的小孩将被吃掉
Do not leave your children unattended. All unattended children will be eaten.
- 有没有看到一头长毛象? - 没有
- Have you seen a mammoth? - No, sorry.
- Have you seen a mammoth? - No.
负鼠?大概11尺高
Possum? About 11 foot tall?
- 有没有看到一头长毛象? - 近在眼前，巨大无比
- Hey, buddy, have you seen a mammoth? - I sure have. Big as life.
- 在哪里? - 我正在看着他
- Where? - I'm looking at him.
不是我啦
Not me.
可怜，不知道自己是长毛象
Poor guy doesn't know he's a mammoth.
- 到处都找不到她 - 说不定她上船了
- I don't see her anywhere. - Maybe she's already on board.
快!这边!
Hurry, this way. Come on.
- 在那里 - 艾丽，救我!
- There it is. - Ellie! Help!
快!跑!
Come on, come on, run!
用力推!
Push.
- 你们走 - 我们不能丢下你
- You guys gotta go. - We're not leaving you.
- 我命令你们! - 艾丽，不要
- I'm not asking. - Ellie, no.
艾丽，别怕!我们去找救兵
Ellie, don't worry. We're going for help.
不要走开
Stay here.
- 救命! - 救命啊!救人啊
- Help us. - Help! Somebody help.
曼尼
Manny.
- 曼尼!  - 是艾丽，她陷在一个洞里
- Manny. - It's Ellie, she's trapped in a cave.
艾丽!
Ellie.
曼尼?
Manny?
- 救命啊! - 我来救你们
- Help! - I'll save you.
这下好了，谁来救他?
Great. Who's gonna save him?
你平常该多刷牙
You really need to brush.
不要怕，跳进去...跳!
OK, OK, OK. Jump in now.
快跳，胆小猫，快点!
Come on, 'fraidy cat. Come on.
你可以的
You can do this, you can do this, you can do this.
相信你的本能，攻击它
Trust your instincts. Attack the water.
我不是水的猎物 我不是你的猎物!
I am not your prey. I am not your prey.
我不是你的猎物!
I am not your prey.
攻击恶水，偷袭猎物
Attack the water. Stalking the prey.
划!踢!连小婴儿都会
Claw, kick. Even babies can do it. Come on.
划!踢!划!踢!
Claw, kick, claw, kick.
嘿!我正在偷袭猎物!
Hey. I'm stalking the prey.
艾迪
Eddie.
你成功了，击败了可恶的水
You did it, buddy. You kicked water's butt.
没什么 动物大多从小会游泳
Nothing to it. Most animals can swim as babies, you know.
可是老虎不会，我故意不说的
Yeah, but not tigers. I left that part out.
他在那里!
There he is.
艾丽，抓住我
Ellie, hold on to me.
曼尼!在你后面!
Manny, Manny, behind you.
他们在那里!
There they are.
安全脱险!
They made it.
我们以为再也看不到你了
We thought we'd never see you again.
我们会活下去!
We're gonna live.
我们会死翘翘!
We're gonna die.
我不走!
Well, I'm not leaving.
爷爷，放开船，洪水退了
Grandpa, let go of the boat. The flood's over.
- 它现在是我的船了 - 快点!走啦，走啦!
- This is my boat now. - Come on, let's go. Come on, come on.
史都，我们活下来了
Stu. We made it. We're gonna live.
至少...我还活着
Well, I am anyway.
我想开一家游泳训练班
I'm thinking about starting a swim school.
叫“希德乌贼补习班”
Sid's Squids.
火王万岁!
All hail Fire King.
嗨
Hi.
火王勇退洪水 加入我们，伟大高贵的猛男
Fire King avert flood. Join us, O great and noble flaming one.
别急、别急，你开的条件不错
No, not so fast there, OK. You make a quality offer.
但火王有别的承诺 这里的同伙需要他
But Fire King has a prior commitment. His herd needs him.
他是死缠烂打的橡皮糖 把我们都黏在一起
He is the gooey, sticky stuff that holds us together.
他是这伙人的灵魂 没有他我们活不下去
He made this herd, and we'd be nothing without him.
- 真的? - 希德 希德
- You mean it? - Sid. Sid.
但不表示我想碰你
That doesn't mean "want to touch".
不要问原因
Don't ask.
我们不是唯二的长毛象了
We're not the last ones anymore.
你不来?
You're not coming?
你想跟他们去?
You wanna go with them?
我是长毛象啊
I am a mammoth.
应该跟长毛像一起
I should probably be with a mammoth.
你觉得咧?
Don't you think?
没错啦，除非...
Yeah, unless...
除非什么?
Unless?
除非我...
Unless I...
我想说的是...
I just wanna say...
我想跟你说...
I need to tell you...
希望你找到想要的东西
I hope you find everything you're looking for.
你也一样
You too.
曼尼? 我们认识后你有长足进步 这当然都是我的功劳
Manny, you've come a long way since we met and I'll take full credit for that,
可是你应该忘掉过去 追求你的未来
but you need to let go of the past so you can have a future.
- 去追她 - 没关系
- Go after her. - It's OK.
我们永远挺你
We'll always be here for you.
- 我会跟你们保持联系 - 知道啦，你够朋友
- I'll keep in touch. - Yeah, yeah. You're a good friend.
废话少说，快走
Point made. Now, go on. Scat.
我们的曼尼长大了
Our Manny's growing up.
艾丽 艾丽
Ellie! Ellie!
曼尼
Manny.
艾丽! 艾丽! 我们在一起不是因为情非得己
Ellie, I don't want us to be together because we have to.
而是因为情投意合
I want us to be together because we want to.
艾丽，我想跟你在一起
And I wanna be with you, Ellie.
- 不知道你愿意吗? - 曼尼，我一直觉得...
- What do you say? - Manny, I thought you were going...
你也有负鼠体贴的一面
You're possum enough for me.
只剩我们两个啦 两个光棍在原野任意闯荡
Well, it's just you and me now. Two bachelors knocking about in the wild.
但我不背你
Fine. But I'm not gonna carry you.
- 我还有尊严 - 看在以往的交情，别这样啦
- I still have my pride, you know. - Come on, buddy, for old time's sake.
我背他
I'll carry him.
- 可是你的同类要走了 - 我要跟我的“同类”一起走
- But your herd's leaving. - We are now.
哇!闪电结婚
Shotgun!
你比较喜欢谁?我还是迪亚戈
Manny, who do you like better? Me or Diego?
- 迪亚戈，你哪有得比 - 哈，我有没有跟你说过?
- Diego. It's not even close. - Told you.
曼尼，对自己孩子不能偏心
Manny, you can't choose between your kids.
我孩子? 他连宠物狗都算不上
He's not my kid. Not even my dog.
如果我养狗、狗生了小狗
If I had a dog and my dog had a kid...
小狗养宠物，那宠物才是希德
and the dog's kid had a pet, that would be Sid.
- 我可以养狗吗，曼尼? - 不行
- Can I have a dog, Manny? - No.
- 艾丽，我可以养狗吗? - 当然可以，亲爱的
- Ellie, can I have a dog? - Of course you can, sweetie.
艾丽，我们不能有两套标准
Ellie, we have to be consistent with him.
我救了你一命，小家伙
I saved you, little buddy.
生什么气，我救了你一命
Calm down. I saved you, little buddy. Remember?